<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
   Test XML file for resolving merge conflicts
    -->
<book1>
    <information>
        <author first_name="Italo" last_name="Calvino">Calvin the Italian</author>
        <title>Translucent Cities</title>
        <inclusions>
            <item tag="headline">Dream-like story-telling at the twilight of an empire</item>
            <item tag="description">In a garden sit the aged <character tag="kublai">Kublai
                    Khan</character> and the young <character tag="polo">Marco Polo</character> --
                Tartar emperor and Venetian traveler. <character tag="kublai">Kublai
                    Khan</character> has sensed the end of his empire coming soon. <character
                    tag="polo">Marco Polo</character> diverts the <character tag="kublai"
                    >emperor</character> with tales of the cities <character tag="polo"
                    >he</character> has seen in <character tag="polo">his</character> travels around
                the empire: cities and memory, cities and desire, cities and designs, cities and the
                dead, cities and the sky, trading cities, hidden cities. Soon it becomes clear that
                each of these fantastic places is really the same place.</item>
        </inclusions>
        <characters>
            <character tag="polo">Marco Polo</character>
            <character tag="kublai">Kublai Khan</character>
        </characters>
    </information>
    <content>
        <pages>
            <city chapter="8" pageBegin="124" pageEnd="125" title="Cities &amp; Names" index="5"
                name="Irene">
                <paragraph><mention>Irene</mention> is the city visible when you lean out from the
                    edge of the plateau at the hour when the lights come on, and in the limpid air,
                    the pink of the settlement can be discerned spread out in the distance below:
                    where the windows are more concentrated, where it thins out in dimply lighted
                    alleys, where it collects the shadows of gardens, where it raises towers with
                    signal fires; and if the evening is misty, a hazy glow swells like a milky
                    sponge at the foot of the gulleys.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>Travelers on the plateau, shepards shifting their flocks, bird-catchers
                    watching their nets, hermits gathering greens: all look down and speak of
                        <mention>Irene</mention>. At times the wind brings a music of bass drums and
                    trumpets, the bang of firecrackers in the light-display of a festival; at times
                    the rattle of guns, the explosion of a powder magazine in the sky yellow with
                    the fires of civil war. Those who look down from the heights conjecture about
                    what is happening in the city; they wonder if it would be pleasant or unpleasant
                    to be in <mention>Irene</mention> that evening. Not that they have any intention
                    of going there (in any case the roads winding down to the valley are bad), but
                        <mention>Irene</mention> is a magnet for the eyes and thoughts of those who
                    stay up above.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>At this point <character tag="kublai">Kublai Khan</character> expects
                        <character tag="polo">Marco</character> to speak of <mention>Irene</mention>
                    as it is seen from within. But Marco cannot do this: he has not succeeded in
                    discovering which is the city that those of the plateau call
                        <mention>Irene</mention>. For that matter, it is of slight importance: if
                    you saw it, standing in its midst, it would be a different city;
                        <mention>Irene</mention> is a name for a city in the distance, and if you
                    approach, it changes.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>For those who pass it without entering, the city is one thing; it is
                    another for those who are trapped by it and never leave. There is a city where
                    you arrive for the first time; and there is another city which you leave never
                    to return. Each deserves a different name; perhaps I have already spoken of
                        <mention>Irene</mention> under other names; perhaps I have spoken only of
                        <mention>Irene</mention>.</paragraph>
            </city>
            <city chapter="8" pageBegin="126" pageEnd="126" title="Cities &amp; The Dead" index="4"
                name="Argia">
                <paragraph>What makes <mention>Argia</mention> different from other cities is that
                    it has earth instead of air. The streets are completely filled with dirt, clay
                    packs the rooms to the ceiling, on every stair another stairway is set in
                    negative, over the roofs of the houses hang layers of rocky terrain like skies
                    with clouds. We do not know if the inhabitants can move about the city, widening
                    the worm tunnels and the crevices where roots twist: the dampness destroys
                    people's bodies and they have scant strength; everyone is better off remaining
                    still, prone; anyway, it is dark.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>From up here, nothing of <mention>Argia</mention> can be seen; some say,
                    "It's down below there," and we can only believe them. The place is deserted. At
                    night, putting your ear to the ground, you can sometimes hear a door
                    slam.</paragraph>
            </city>
            <city chapter="8" pageBegin="128" pageEnd="128" title="Continuous Cities" index="2"
                name="Trude">
                <paragraph>If on arriving at <mention>Trude</mention> I had not read the city's name
                    written in big letters, I would have thought I was landing at the same
                        <anachronism object="airplane">airport</anachronism> from which I had taken
                    off. The <anachronism>suburbs</anachronism> they <anachronism object="car"
                        >drove</anachronism> me through were no different from the others, with the
                    same little greenish and yellowish <anachronism object="house"
                        >houses</anachronism>. Following the same signs we swung around the same
                    flower beds in the same squares. The <anachronism object="urban city"
                        >downtown</anachronism> streets displayed goods, packages, signs that had
                    not changed at all. This was the first time I had come to
                        <mention>Trude</mention>, but I already knew the <anachronism object="hotel"
                        >hotel</anachronism> where I happened to be lodged; I had already heard and
                    spoken my dialogues with the buyers and sellers of hardware; I had ended other
                    days identically, looking through the same goblets at the same swaying
                    navels.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>Why come to <mention>Trude</mention>? <character tag="polo">I</character>
                    asked myself. And I already wanted to leave.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>"You can resume your <anachronism object="airplane">flight</anachronism>
                    whenever you like," they said to me, "but you will arrive at another
                        <mention>Trude</mention>, absolutely the same, detail by detail. The world
                    is covered by a sole <mention>Trude</mention> which does not begin and does not
                    end. Only the name of the <anachronism object="airplane">airport</anachronism>
                    changes."</paragraph>
            </city>
        </pages>
        <back_cover>
            <metadata_include tag="headline" type="headline"/>
            <metadata_include tag="description"/>
        </back_cover>
    </content>
</book1>
