<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<hobbit>
    <cast>
        <character id="bilbo" heritage="hobbit" alignment="neutral"/>
        <character id="gandalf" heritage="wizard" alignment="good"/>
        <character id="thorin" heritage="dwarf" alignment="good"/>
        <character id="dwalin" heritage="dwarf" alignment="good"/>
        <character id="balin" heritage="dwarf" alignment="good"/>
        <character id="kili" heritage="dwarf" alignment="good"/>
        <character id="fili" heritage="dwarf" alignment="good"/>
        <character id="bombur" heritage="dwarf" alignment="good"/>
        <character id="bifur" heritage="dwarf" alignment="good"/>
        <character id="bofur" heritage="dwarf" alignment="good"/>
        <character id="dori" heritage="dwarf" alignment="good"/>
        <character id="nori" heritage="dwarf" alignment="good"/>
        <character id="ori" heritage="dwarf" alignment="good"/>
        <character id="oin" heritage="dwarf" alignment="good"/>
        <character id="gloin" heritage="dwarf" alignment="good"/>
        <character id="smaug" heritage="dragon" alignment="evil"/>
        <place id="theHill" type="landmark"/>
        <place id="theWater" type="river"/>
        <place id="bagEnd" type="hobbitHole"/>
        <place id="dale" type="town"/>
        <place id="theMountain" type="mountain"/>
        <place id="mirkwood" type="forest"/>
        <place id="moria" type="mine"/>
    </cast>
    <chapter n="1" title="An Unexpected Party">

        <paragraph>In a hole in the ground there lived a <character ref="bilbo" heritage="hobbit">hobbit</character>.
            Not a nasty, dirty, wet hole, filled with the ends of worms and an oozy smell, nor yet a dry,
            bare, sandy hole with nothing in it to sit down on or to eat: it was a hobbit-hole, and that
            means comfort.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>It had a perfectly round door like a porthole, painted green, with a shiny yellow brass
            knob in the exact middle. The door opened on to a tube-shaped hall like a tunnel: a very
            comfortable tunnel without smoke, with panelled walls, and floors tiled and carpeted, provided
            with polished chairs, and lots and lots of pegs for hats and coats — the <character ref="bilbo"
                heritage="hobbit">hobbit</character> was fond of visitors. The tunnel wound on and on, going
            fairly but not quite straight into the side of <place ref="theHill">The Hill</place> — <place
                ref="theHill">The Hill</place>, as all the people for many miles round called it — and many
            little round doors opened out of it, first on one side and then on another.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>This <character ref="bilbo" heritage="hobbit">hobbit</character> was a very well-to-do
            hobbit, and his name was <character ref="bilbo" heritage="hobbit">Baggins</character>. The
            Bagginses had lived in the neighbourhood of <place ref="theHill">The Hill</place> for time out
            of mind, and people considered them very respectable, not only because most of them were rich,
            but also because they never had any adventures or did anything unexpected: you could tell what a
            Baggins would say on any question without the bother of asking him. This is a story of how a
            Baggins had an adventure, and found himself doing and saying things altogether
            unexpected.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>The mother of our particular <character ref="bilbo" heritage="hobbit">hobbit</character> —
            what is a hobbit? I suppose hobbits need some description nowadays, since they have become rare
            and shy of the Big People, as they call us. They are (or were) a little people, about half our
            height, and smaller than the bearded dwarves. Hobbits have no beards. There is little or no
            magic about them, except the ordinary everyday sort which helps them to disappear quietly and
            quickly when large stupid folk like you and me come blundering along, making a noise like
            elephants which they can hear a mile off.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>Now you know enough to go on with. As I was saying, the mother of this
            <character ref="bilbo" heritage="hobbit">hobbit</character> — of <character ref="bilbo"
                heritage="hobbit">Bilbo Baggins</character>, that is — was the famous Belladonna Took, one of
            the three remarkable daughters of the Old Took, head of the hobbits who lived across
            <place ref="theWater">The Water</place>, the small river that ran at the foot of
            <place ref="theHill">The Hill</place>.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>By some curious chance one morning long ago in the quiet of the world, when there was
            less noise and more green, and the hobbits were still numerous and prosperous, and
            <character ref="bilbo" heritage="hobbit">Bilbo Baggins</character> was standing at his door after
            breakfast smoking an enormous long wooden <item type="object">pipe</item> that reached nearly
            down to his woolly toes — <character ref="gandalf" heritage="wizard">Gandalf</character> came by.
            <character ref="gandalf" heritage="wizard">Gandalf</character>! If you had heard only a quarter of
            what I have heard about him, and I have only heard very little of all there is to hear, you
            would be prepared for any sort of remarkable tale. Tales and adventures sprouted up all over the
            place wherever he went, in the most extraordinary fashion.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>All that the unsuspecting <character ref="bilbo" heritage="hobbit">Bilbo</character> saw that
            morning was an old man with a staff. He had a tall pointed blue hat, a long grey cloak, a
            silver scarf over which his long white beard hung down below his waist, and immense black
            boots.</paragraph>

        <paragraph><said who="bilbo">"Good Morning!"</said> said <character ref="bilbo" heritage="hobbit"
            >Bilbo</character>, and he meant it. The sun was shining, and the grass was very green. But
            <character ref="gandalf" heritage="wizard">Gandalf</character> looked at him from under long bushy
            eyebrows that stuck out further than the brim of his shady hat.</paragraph>

        <paragraph><said who="gandalf">"What do you mean?"</said> he said. <said who="gandalf">"Do you wish
                me a good morning, or mean that it is a good morning whether I want it or not; or that you
                feel good this morning; or that it is a morning to be good on?"</said></paragraph>

        <paragraph><said who="bilbo">"All of them at once,"</said> said <character ref="bilbo" heritage="hobbit"
            >Bilbo</character>. <said who="bilbo">"And a very fine morning for a pipe of tobacco out of
                doors, into the bargain. If you have a pipe about you, sit down and have a fill of mine!
                There's no hurry, we have all the day before us!"</said> Then <character ref="bilbo"
                heritage="hobbit">Bilbo</character> sat down on a seat by his door, crossed his legs, and blew
            out a beautiful grey ring of smoke that sailed up into the air without breaking and floated away
            over <place ref="theHill">The Hill</place>.</paragraph>

        <paragraph><said who="gandalf">"Very pretty!"</said> said <character ref="gandalf" heritage="wizard"
            >Gandalf</character>. <said who="gandalf">"But I have no time to blow smoke-rings this morning.
                I am looking for someone to share in an adventure that I am arranging, and it's very
                difficult to find anyone."</said></paragraph>

        <paragraph><said who="bilbo">"I should think so — in these parts! We are plain quiet folk and have
                no use for adventures. Nasty disturbing uncomfortable things! Make you late for dinner! I
                can't think what anybody sees in them,"</said> said our <character ref="bilbo" heritage="hobbit"
            >Mr. Baggins</character>, and stuck one thumb behind his bheritages, and blew out another even
            bigger smoke-ring. Then he took out his morning letters, and began to read, pretending to take
            no more notice of the old man.</paragraph>

        <paragraph><said who="gandalf">"What a lot of things you do use Good morning for!"</said> said
            <character ref="gandalf" heritage="wizard">Gandalf</character>. <said who="gandalf">"Now you mean
                that you want to get rid of me, and that it won't be good till I move off."</said></paragraph>

        <paragraph><said who="gandalf">"I am Gandalf, and Gandalf means me! To think that I should have
                lived to be good-morninged by Belladonna Took's son, as if I was selling buttons at the
                door!"</said></paragraph>

        <paragraph><said who="bilbo">"Gandalf, Gandalf! Good gracious me! Not the wandering wizard that gave
                Old Took a pair of magic diamond studs that fastened themselves and never came undone till
                ordered? Not the fellow who used to tell such wonderful tales at parties, about dragons and
                goblins and giants and the rescue of princesses and the unexpected luck of widows' sons? Not
                the man that used to make such particularly excellent fireworks!"</said></paragraph>

        <paragraph>Just before tea-time there came a tremendous ring on the front-door bell, and then
            <character ref="bilbo" heritage="hobbit">he</character> remembered! He rushed and put on the
            kettle, and put out another cup and saucer, and an extra cake or two, and ran to the door. It
            was not <character ref="gandalf" heritage="wizard">Gandalf</character> at all. It was
            <character ref="dwalin" heritage="dwarf">a dwarf with a blue beard tucked into a golden belt</character>,
            and very bright eyes under his dark-green hood. As soon as the door was opened, he pushed
            inside, just as if he had been expected. He hung his hooded cloak on the nearest peg.</paragraph>

        <paragraph><said who="dwalin">"Dwalin at your service!"</said> he said with a low bow.</paragraph>

        <paragraph><said who="bilbo">"Bilbo Baggins at yours!"</said> said the <character ref="bilbo"
                heritage="hobbit">hobbit</character>, too surprised to ask any questions for the moment.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>They had not been at table long, in fact they had hardly reached the third cake, when
            there came another even louder ring at the bell. It was not <character ref="gandalf" heritage="wizard"
            >Gandalf</character>. Instead there was a very old-looking <character ref="balin" heritage="dwarf"
            >dwarf on the step with a white beard and a scarlet hood</character>; and he too hopped inside
            as soon as the door was open, just as if he had been invited.</paragraph>

        <paragraph><said who="balin">"Balin at your service!"</said> he said with his hand on his
            breast.</paragraph>

        <paragraph><said who="bilbo">"Thank you!"</said> said <character ref="bilbo" heritage="hobbit"
            >Bilbo</character> with a gasp.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>And so the evening wore on. <character ref="thorin" heritage="dwarf">Thorin</character>
            spread a piece of <item type="document">parchment rather like a map</item> on the table in the
            light of a big lamp with a red shade. <said who="gandalf">"This was made by
                <character ref="thorin" heritage="dwarf">Thror</character>, your grandfather,
                <character ref="thorin" heritage="dwarf">Thorin</character>,"</said> he said. <said who="gandalf"
            >"It is a plan of <place ref="theMountain">the Mountain</place>."</said></paragraph>

        <paragraph><said who="thorin">"I don't see that this will help us much,"</said> said
            <character ref="thorin" heritage="dwarf">Thorin</character> disappointedly after a glance.
            <said who="thorin">"I remember <place ref="theMountain">the Mountain</place> well enough
                and the lands about it. And I know where <place ref="mirkwood">Mirkwood</place> is, and the
                Withered Heath where the great dragons bred."</said></paragraph>

        <paragraph><said who="gandalf">"There is one point that you haven't noticed,"</said> said
            <character ref="gandalf" heritage="wizard">the wizard</character>, <said who="gandalf">"and that is
                the secret entrance."</said></paragraph>

        <paragraph>As they sang the <character ref="bilbo" heritage="hobbit">hobbit</character> felt the love of
            beautiful things made by hands and by cunning and by magic moving through him, a fierce and a
            jealous love, the desire of the hearts of dwarves. Then something Tookish woke up inside him,
            and he wished to go and see the great mountains, and hear the pine-trees and the waterfalls, and
            explore the caves, and wear a sword instead of a walking-stick. He looked out of the window. The
            stars were out in a dark sky above the trees. He thought of the jewels of the dwarves shining in
            dark caverns. Suddenly in the wood beyond <place ref="theWater">The Water</place> a flame leapt
            up — probably somebody lighting a wood-fire — and he thought of plundering <character ref="smaug"
                heritage="dragon">dragons</character> settling on his quiet
            <place ref="theHill">Hill</place> and kindling it all to flames. He shuddered.</paragraph>

    </chapter>
</hobbit>
